remember that 9/11 was the greatest
intelligence failure in the CIA's
history. 3,000 Americans were killed
because we didn't do our jobs. I ran
into a a colleague of mine in the
hallway. So I said, "Hey, where have you
been?" And he whispered, "I've been in
Afghanistan." I said, "What are you
doing in Afghanistan?" And he said, "I'm
killing people. What do you think I'm
doing?" Now, these are people who just
walk into your embassy and say, "I know
where Osama bin Laden is, and I want a
million dollars or $10 million." Okay,
I'll tell you one thing about ISI too is
they weren't afraid of anybody. And
ISI major in Lahore said you can't you
can't run a counterterrorism operation
from a four-star hotel. And so we gave
we gave the Pakistani government $5
million. We gave them 10 million for
Khaled Shake Muhammad and a million
here, a million there. And then we
bought equipment and we bought, you
know, whatever equipment we shipped in
for the operations. We just told them,
just keep it. Just keep all of it. We're
not going to take any of it back. Just
consider it a gift.
Like everybody else in the building, I I
volunteered to go to Afghanistan and I
was actually denied three times. And
then I ran into a a colleague of mine in
the hallway and I hadn't seen him in
months. So I said, "Hey, where have you
been?" And he whispered, "I've been in
Afghanistan." I said, "What are you
doing in Afghanistan?" And he said, "I'm
killing people. What do you think I'm
doing?" And that's when I realized that
they didn't need an Arabic translator.
So, I went to the uh the deputy director
for counterterrorism and I said very
angrily, "If you don't send me over
there right now, I'm going to resign and
I'm going to go to Exxon and I'm going
to take my Arabic with me." He said,
"Relax, relax. Do you want to go to
Pakistan?" I said, "Yes. When?" He said,
"Tomorrow." I said, "Done. What do you
want me to do there?" He said, "I want
you to be the head of counterterrorism
operations." And I said, "Okay." And so
the next day I went
remember that 9/11 was the greatest
intelligence failure in the CIA's
history. 3,000 Americans were killed
because we didn't do our jobs. And so
there was this very deep desire for
revenge. And as I was leaving the office
for that last day, I was going to fly to
a slum about the next morning. My boss
pulled me aside and he whispered to me,
"Kill them all." And I said I said,
"Really? We've We've already gotten to
that. Kill them all.
I'm not going to do that.
[Music]
I spent most of my day either at ISI or
working with ISI officers or meeting
with ISI officers or, you know, we did
everything jointly, everything hand
glove. So, the job itself, it this
wasn't just me. This was this was my
Pakistani colleagues as well. Uh it was
severalfold. It was to carry out
operations to capture al-Qaeda fighters
who had taken refuge in Pakistan. On my
very first day, my boss said to me, "We
need to come up with a standard
operating procedure for how we do this."
Because we had never done anything like
this before. And I said, "I have an
idea. you know, we have these people in
villages all up and down the the the
border between Pakistan and Afghanistan.
I said, it's very inefficient and it's
dangerous and they're not able to do
anything. I think we should take
everybody off the border and just let
al-Qaeda come into Pakistan
because, you know, they're going to go
to safe houses and then with the
Pakistanis we can raid the safe houses
and catch everybody at the same time.
And that is exactly what they did. you
know they were going to make a mistake.
You know they were going to get on their
cell phone or get on their Hotmail
account or Gmail account or go into the
market to buy vegetables or tea or
chicken or whatever and we caught them.
We caught hundreds of them. Hundreds of
them. So a lot of the time I spent
planning these operations
My Pakistani colleagues would come and
say, "We have a lead. We have an
address." And we're told that there are
Arabs in this address. Or a friendly
Arab intelligence officer would call me
and say, "I think I have an address. I
heard there's somebody from Islamic
Jihad." So I'd call ISI and say, "I have
an address." They say, "We have an
address." We create some teams. We break
the door down at 2 o'clock in the
morning, grab everybody inside, and it
was success after success after success.
Number one. Number two is, and this is
not unique to Islamabad, but every
American embassy around the world, every
every embassy around the world, no
matter the country, gets something
called walk-ins. Now, these are people
who just walk into your embassy and say,
"I know where Osama bin Laden is, and I
want a million dollars or $10 million."
Okay, how do you know where Osama bin
Laden is? Well, I I washed dishes at
this uh restaurant and I heard somebody
talking. Okay, thank you. If you know,
if we catch him, we'll give you the $10
million, but thanks for coming in. You
can leave now. 99% of the people who
walk in are insane. They are
fabricators, liars, just seeing if they
can get some money from you. They are
intelligence peddlers, which means what
they're saying is true, but they're also
going to the British embassy, the French
embassy, the German embassy, the Russian
embassy, the Chinese embassy to get more
money. 1%
are real. In Islamabad, we had walk-ins
every single day, sometimes several in
one day. Now, in other embassies I've
worked in, we might get three or four a
year. In Islamabad, every single day,
and most of the time, they were people
just looking for some money, but
sometimes they had actionable,
real intelligence. And I would turn it
over to ISI. They would investigate and
then together we would do the operation.
The third thing,
Pakistan is a big country with a lot of
people and while I'm in Islamabad doing
my job every day, we have to think about
what's happening in Peshawar, in
Karachi, in Lahore, in Qua and all over
the place. Now, of course, ISI has
offices in all of these places. So they
would call Islamabad, Islamabad would
call me. I I'm happy to say I got to see
the whole country which was very
exciting and very beautiful. Those were
the three things and and it made for
extraordinarily long work days. I don't
think I ever worked less than 14 hours a
day in the entire time that I was there
just because there was so much going on.
My experience with ISI was 100%
positive. These guys became like my
brothers. I'll tell you one thing about
ISI too is they weren't afraid of
anybody. When we would go out on these
operations, we would always take the FBI
with us. We had bulletproof vests and
all kinds of things. ISI didn't. They
had just the clothes they were wearing.
They were not afraid of anybody. And I
learned a great deal from them. You
know, almost to a man, at least among
the the ISI officers that I was working
with, they were trained almost
exclusively in the UK at Sandhurst,
very very professional.
And so I could rely on them for advice.
Like I I was new to the country.
I didn't know anything about Pakistani
history or culture. My entire adult life
was spent in the Middle East. And so
they they taught me they taught me about
the culture and the history and how you
deal with different people, how you
conduct an interrogation the Pakistani
way. So I learned a great deal. But on
top of their professionalism, they were
just genuinely good people. I met their
families. We would all go out to dinner
together.
[Music]
The Pakistani method of interrogation
was far more direct and um and efficient
than the American uh the American way of
doing it. The American I let me let me
fix that than the CIA way of doing it.
The FBI has its own way which is very
slow and deliberate but it works. The
CIA way is to have a good cop and a bad
cop. So you have one person who's being
nice to the to the prisoner and another
one who's threatening to beat or kill
the prisoner. That rarely works. The
Pakistanis did not waste any time. They
would just say, "Look, you're in
trouble. You're in big trouble. Things
can get bad from here or they can get
good from here. So I suggest you start
answering questions." And nine times out
of 10, they would sit there and answer
the questions. You didn't have to
threaten them. You didn't have to beat
them. You didn't have to take them to a
secret site halfway around the world and
torture them or put a gun to their head
and play Russian roulette. You just
said, "Look, this is the reality right
now. You are a prisoner and this can be
easy or it can be terrible. Make it
easy." And they got results.
Guantanamo aside, the others I I learned
as they were being created. And I
remember saying to a colleague, "How is
this legal? I don't understand how this
is legal. It's it's extr territorial. I
just don't understand what it's based
on, how we can get away with doing
this." Um, Guantanamo
was different. Colonel Tonic came to me
one day in uh in Islamabad and he said,
"Listen, the Raml Piney jail is full.
Like, it's literally full. You have to
take these Arabs and you have to take
them somewhere else. We can't keep them
forever. So, I called the CIA's
counterterrorism center and I said, "ISI
is telling me that the jail is full and
they want us to take these guys out. So,
what do I do with them?" And I was told,
"Put them on a C12 cargo plane, Air
Force cargo plane, and send them to
Guantanamo." And I said, "Guanto, Cuba?
Yes." I said, "Why in the world would we
send them to Cuba?" And my colleague
said, "Well, we have an idea.
We're going to keep them in Guantanamo
for 2 or 3 weeks and then we'll send
them to the federal district court where
their crime was committed, New York,
Boston, or Washington." And I said,
"That's a great idea." Well, there was
never any intention of putting these
people on trial because, as you said,
90% of them were innocent of any crime.
They were Afghan farmers or or
nobbodyies or Arabs married to Afghan
women. Um they hadn't committed any
crime. A lot of them were turned in by
neighbors that maybe they had a land
dispute with or they owed they were owed
money from.
What better way to not pay your debt
than to tell the Americans this guy is
with al-Qaeda. And so you know at at its
height we had 770 people at Guantanamo.
Now we have what 34 33 and and half of
them will be released soon. But um but
the idea for Guantanamo was temporary at
best because they were going to go on
trial in the United States and then they
never did.
The State Department manages the the
federal what's it called? The federal
[Music]
there's a name for it. It's the program
that gives rewards for the capture of
terrorists. We gave the Pakistani
government $5 million. We gave them 10
million for Khalik Muhammad and a
million here, a million there. And then
we bought equipment and we bought, you
know, whatever equipment we shipped in
for the operations. We just told them
just keep it. Just keep all of it. We're
not going to take any of it back. Just
consider it a gift. I don't know what
the total amount of money is and I don't
know what happened to the money.
This is another one of those times when
ISI really helped me a lot. Uh because
we were, you know, as we were setting up
for the abused operation, we were just
staying in in a hotel. We had rented the
entire floor of one of Lahore's biggest
hotels.
And
ISI major in Lahore said, "You can't you
can't run a counterterrorism operation
from a four-star hotel.
You you have to find a house." house. I
said, "How the heck am I going to find a
house? I don't speak any of the
languages in this country." And what am
I going to say? I need a house where I
can do interrogations at the same time.
So, he said, "Look, we'll go together."
So, two Americans,
a friend of mine and and I went with
this major
um and uh we found a real estate agent.
The major said we needed the biggest
house that they had
uh because we entertain a great deal of
time and the house needed to be huge for
the big dinners and big parties and
receptions that we had. He ended up
getting us a 10bedroom 10b house in
Lahore and a 7-bedroom 7b house in
Fisalaba. And they were absolutely
perfect. They were expensive, but they
were perfect because we caught so many
al-Qaeda people that night that we
needed every one of those bedrooms to do
interrogations in. That's what they
ended up serving as.
My very first week, my boss said, "Come
up with a standard operating procedure
for taking down an al-Qaeda safe house."
Of course, we had something called high
value targets, HVTs. And that was the
the obvious list. It was it was bin
Laden, Zawahari, Abu Zuba, Khalichek,
Muhammad, Ramsey, Benes, the usual cast
of characters. And those people who were
that cooperative would remain in ISI
custody. We believed at the time that
Abu Zuba was the number three in
al-Qaeda. He was not. In fact, he had
never joined al-Qaeda. He worked along
with al-Qaeda. We had very, very
specific orders that we had to take him
alive because he was this terrorist
superman and that he could lead us to
bin Laden. George Tennant called the
director of the CIA and he told me,
these were his exact words, he said, 247
CIA eyes on. So, I tore up a sheet and I
tied him to the bed from his wrists and
his ankles. And then I put the ceiling
fan on high to make it uncomfortably
cold so that I wouldn't fall asleep. And
I sat there like this in a chair at the
foot of his bed. And I just stared at
him. The entire interrogation program uh
at the CIA uh they called it enhanced
interrogation techniques. I called it a
torture program. The entire program was
a criminal act. I was ready to die for
my country out there and it was all
based on a lie. And so I've become very
much an activist over the last 20 years
to release Abu Zubeda and to apologize
to this was a a war crime or a crime
against humanity. It's a dark stain on
the modern history of the United States.